Rajath Jaiprakash

🜎 rajathjn | in rajath-jaiprakash | 🏶 Portfolio | 🗷 rajathjnx@gmail.com | 🖫 +91-9900852849

Summary

Site Reliability Engineer - 2 with around **3 years** of specialized experience in **Infrastructure Automation**, **CI/CD pipelines**, and **Logging/Monitoring pipelines**. Delivered **50%** reduction in manual operations by designing and implementing **20+ Ansible** roles across production environments. Demonstrated expertise in troubleshooting complex infrastructure issues by reducing system downtime by **30%** through enhanced observability solutions.

Skills

Programming	Python, Bash Scripting, C++, Powershell, CI/CD (GitHub Actions/Jenkins)
Tools	Ansible, Docker, Kubernetes, Elastic Stack (ELK), InfluxDB, Grafana, Telegraf, NagiosXI
Certifications	The Linux Foundation: LFS162, Red Hat Certified Engineer (EX294)

Work Experience

Akamai Technologies, Inc. | Site Reliability Engineer 2

Oct 2024 - Present

- Architected end-to-end CI/CD pipelines for our Access Border Routers by integrating it with our Simulator and
 custom deployment scripts, reducing deployment time by 75% and reducing our downtime to just 30 seconds.
- Engineered fault-tolerant system by developing **Python** based auto-remediation scripts for **8 critical services**, eliminating **85%** of previously manual recovery procedures and maintaining **90%** service availability.
- Identified, Troubleshooted and Solved a Business critical compliance issue which impacted our 6WIND VSRs, across 18 Distributed Edge sites, in a time span of 3 days.

Akamai Technologies, Inc. | Site Reliability Engineer

July 2022 - Oct 2024

- Improved our deployment workflow by crafting 20+ Ansible roles for automated configuration management, reducing deployment errors by 65% and cutting rollout time from days to hours across 4 environments.
- Executed the complex migration of 18 production logging servers by designing comprehensive transition plan and implementing parallel cutover strategy, maintaining 100% service availability and processing 250K+ daily transactions without interruption.
- Spearheaded DevOps knowledge sharing initiative by conducting 6 technical workshops for 30+ engineers over 3 different time-zones, resulting in 40% fewer deployment-related incidents across development teams.
- Transformed logging infrastructure by migrating and optimizing Elastic Stack deployment for 150GB+ of daily logs, accelerating log search performance by 300% and enabling real-time anomaly detection for 20+ critical services.
- Revitalized monitoring system by implementing hierarchical alert structure in NagiosXI and InfluxDB for 200+
 nodes, decreasing false positives and redundant alerts by 70% and reducing mean time to identification from 10
 minutes to 30 seconds, During my Internship.

Projects

ClipForge - AI Driven Video Processing Pipeline

- Engineered an end-to-end local and open-source automated video generation pipeline by integrating WhisperX, FFm-peg, and AI agents created using Langchain Python. Project has received over 77k+ impressions to date.
- Constructed intelligent metadata generation system by leveraging AI-based text processing algorithms, improving SEO optimization and increasing content discoverability by 40%. Created the automated testing flow by building CI/CD pipelines using Github Actions.
- Devised portable containerized solution by implementing **Dockerized** deployment workflow. Integrated real-time monitoring system by developing **Discord notification services**, providing instantaneous updates on processing status for **100+ daily video operations**.

Education

PES University, Bangalore

• B.Tech in Electronics and Communication Engineering (GPA: 8.99)

2018 - 2022

• B.Tech Minors in Computer Science and Engineering

2018 - 2022

Extras

IEEE Paper: Analog Front End Modelling of Miniature CMOS Image Sensor

Led a cross-functional research team by coordinating circuit design and simulation efforts, resulting in the publication
of an innovative medical imaging technology with potential applications in minimally invasive procedures with a power
consumption of just 4.8 mW.